<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Access Connecticut</string>

    <string name="the_bill" formatted="false">
        <![CDATA[

Access Connecticut is seeking to have this proposed legislation introduced and enacted into law in the legislative session which begins January 2017.<br>

<b>Access to original birth certificates by adult adopted persons</b><br>
Section 1. Subsection (c) of section 7-53 of the general statutes is repealed and the following is substituted in lieu thereof (Effective July 1, 2017):
(c) Upon request, the department shall issue an uncertified copy of an original certificate of birth to (1) an adopted person who is eighteen years of age or older [whose adoption was finalized on or after October 1, 1983], or (2) such adopted person’s adult child or grandchild. Such certificate shall be marked with a notation by the issuer that such original certificate of birth has been superseded by a replacement certificate of birth as on file. Additionally, a notice stating that information related to the birth parents’ preferences regarding contact by such adopted person or such adopted person’s adult child or grandchild and a medical health history form completed by the birth parent may be on file with the Department of Children and Families shall be printed on such certificate or attached thereto.
Sec. 2. Section 7-53a of the general statutes is repealed and the following is substituted in lieu thereof (Effective July 1, 2017):
(a) Not later than January 1, [2016] 2018, and annually thereafter until January 1, [2021] 2023, the Commissioner of Public Health shall submit a report, in accordance with the provisions of section 11-4a, concerning the number of original birth certificates issued annually to adopted persons eighteen years of age or older [whose adoption was finalized on or after October 1, 1983], or the adult children or grandchildren of adopted persons in accordance with section 7-53, to the joint standing committee of the General Assembly having cognizance of matters relating to public health.
(b) Not later than January 1, [2016] 2018, and annually thereafter until January 1, [2021] 2023, the Commissioner of Children and Families shall submit a report, in accordance with the provisions of section 11-4a, concerning the number of contact preference forms and medical health history forms annually filed with the department in accordance with section 17a-60a to the joint standing committee of the General Assembly having cognizance of matters relating to public health. The report shall include the number of birth parents that selected each option described in section 17a-60a.
Sec. 3. Subsection (c) of section 45a-751b of the general statutes is repealed and the following is substituted in lieu thereof (Effective July 1, 2017):
(c) Regardless of the date parental rights were terminated, on or after July 1, [2015] 2017, the Department of Public Health shall, upon request, issue an uncertified copy of an original birth certificate to an adopted person eighteen years of age or older who is the subject of the birth certificate [and whose adoption was finalized on or after October 1, 1983], or such adopted person’s adult child or grandchild, in accordance with the provisions of section 7-53.
Sec. 4. Subsection (a) of section 45a-751c of the general statutes is repealed and the following is substituted in lieu thereof (Effective July 1, 2017):
(a) On the petition of an adopted person who is eighteen years of age or older [and whose adoption was finalized prior to October 1, 1983], or such adopted person’s adult child or grandchild, the Probate Court or the Superior Court that finalized an adoption or appointed a guardian ad litem in accordance with section 45a-753 shall issue an order directing the Department of Public Health to issue an uncertified copy of an original birth certificate to such adopted person or such adopted person’s child or grandchild in accordance with subsection (b) of section 7-53, provided each birth parent named on the original birth certificate: (1) Consents to the release of identifying information in accordance with sections 45a-751 to 45a-751b, inclusive; (2) is deceased; or (3) a legal representative or guardian ad litem consents to the release of identifying information on behalf of the birth parent in accordance with section 45a-753. Nothing in this section shall limit the right of an adopted person eighteen years of age or older [whose adoption was finalized on or after October 1, 1983], or such adopted person’s adult child or grandchild to obtain an uncertified copy of an original birth certificate pursuant to section 7-53.
Sec. 5. (NEW) (Effective July 1, 2017): When it shall be impossible through good-faith efforts to provide an uncertified copy of an original birth certificate to an adopted person eighteen years of age or older pursuant to section 1 of this act, such as in the case of an adopted person born outside of, but whose adoption was finalized in Connecticut, such adopted person shall have the right to secure from a court of competent jurisdiction or the child-placing agency, as defined in section 45a-707 of the general statutes, that was involved in the adoption of such person, the true and correct identifying information that would have appeared on his or her original birth certificate.
[Proposed deletions are red and [enclosed in brackets]. Proposed additions are green and underlined.]


        ]]>
    </string>

    <string name="facts" formatted="false">
        <![CDATA[

<b>Facts About Access to Original Birth Certificates</b><br>
You might have some questions about restoring the right of adult adoptees to access their original birth certificates. Here’s some information to get you started:

<br><b>1. Biological heritage matters.</b><br>
It is morally and ethically wrong for the State to deprive a human being of access to their biological heritage.
There is no substitute for the truth, particularly the truth about oneself. The truth is that adoptees have two heritages, two identities, two families and two ancestries. It serves no one, least of all adoptees themselves, to pretend this isn’t true.
<br><b>2. The law discriminates against adult adoptees solely because they are adopted.</b><br>
Every non-adopted adult citizen of Connecticut has the right to receive a copy of their true, original, true birth certificate. Yet the State denies this right to adult adoptees, forever, simply because they are adopted. That’s called discrimination, and it’s wrong.
<br><b>3. Adoptees are deprived of the ability to obtain current, updated medical information that is crucial to their health.</b><br>
Adult adoptees walk into a doctor’s office and have to write “I don’t know” in the medical history section of the intake form. Increasingly we know that having accurate information about your medical history is crucial to staying healthy. A history of breast or colon cancer, heart disease, diabetes, high blood pressure or cholesterol, impacts decisions made today about tests and treatment. Any medical information that may be contained in an adoptee’s file is at least two decades old, and often incomplete or non-existent.

<br><b>4. There aren’t any effective substitutes for the right of access to a true, original birth certificate.</b><br>
The point of access to original birth certificates isn’t search and reunion, although some adoptees will use the information that way. However, if the point were search and reunion, intermediary systems and reunion registries don’t work.
Many adoptees won’t use these systems because they are so humiliating and degrading. Can you imagine having to approach a social worker, pay a search fee of up to several hundred dollars, and possibly submit to counseling (!) to get a copy of your birth certificate?  And many birth mothers won’t use them because they believe they don’t have the right.
For a variety of reasons, reunion registries have an abysmal success rate (~2%). They require both people to be searching, both people to be alive, and both people to be aware of their existence. “The stars have to align” perfectly, and of course they often don’t.

<br><b>5. Adoptees have proved themselves to be extraordinarily sensitive to the possible concerns of their birth parents.</b><br>
Other states and countries that have enacted retroactive OBC access laws report a complete lack of “horror stories”, and “extraordinary compliance” with biological parents preferences regarding contact. “None of the dangers people had feared – that their privacy would be invaded and their families destroyed – had materialized.”

<br><h1>About Birthparents</h1><br>
(Note: Birth/first parents, and particularly birth/first mothers, are the object of much misinformation and negative stereotyping in our society. We have volunteer birth/first parents who would be happy to answer your questions personally.)

<br><b>1. The vast majority of birth/first mothers want contact with their adult offspring.</b><br>
A great deal of research shows that the vast majority of birth/first mothers, (90-95%) want at least some contact with their adult offspring. In states which have enacted access laws with Contact Preference Forms, for example, less than 1% of forms filed indicate a preference for no contact. Organizations conducting searches for adoptees under other state’s laws, such as New Jersey, report that 95% of birth/first mothers consent to at least some contact.

<br><b>2. Birth/first parents who don’t want contact don’t have to have it.</b><br>
The bill proposed by Access provides a system for birth/first parents to file a Contact Preference Form (used successfully in other states) which provides them with the following options:
	I would like to be contacted;
	I would prefer to be contacted only through an intermediary; or
	I prefer not to be contacted at this time.
We have a right to freedom of association in this country. Birth/first parents who do not wish to have contact do not have to have it. They can just say “no”. They are adults after all, and due to biological realities birth/first parents are at least in their thirties (and more likely much older).  Adoptees have been searching for and finding their birth/first parents for years (especially since the advent of the internet) and the tiny percentage of birth/first parents who don’t want contact can say “no”.
<br><b>3. Adoptees and birth/first parents are natural allies, not natural enemies.</b><br>
Adult adoptees are not, as a group, stalkers, idiots or insensitive louts. Adoptees instead tend to be quite sensitive to the possible concerns of their birth/first parents. Several states and, in fact, entire countries that have restored access report this is their experience. Remember that birth/first parents are adoptee’s blood relatives. We’re not out to hurt them.

<br><b>4. For the past thirty years in Connecticut, every birth/first parent has signed a sworn Affidavit stating that they know their identities could be discovered by their adult offspring.</b><br>
Since 1983 every birth/first parent in Connecticut has signed a sworn Affidavit of Consent to Termination of Parental Rights that states, in part, “I am aware that the child, upon reaching his eighteenth birthday, may have the right to information which may identify me or other blood relatives.”
Affidavit for Consent to Termination of Parental Rights, CT Form JD-JM-60 Rev. 7-11

<br><b>5. At all times prior 1974, Connecticut law allowed adult adoptees over the age of 18 to access their original birth certificate.</b><br>
The law was explicit and clear. In fact, many adoption agencies provided the adoptive parents with the child’s birth name on documents such as placement agreements and adoption decrees. So prior to 1974 any social worker or adoption agency who told a birth/first mother that her child would never know her identity was misinforming her about the law.
<br><b>6. Complete birth/first parent anonymity is an illusion under Connecticut law.</b><br>
Connecticut Probate Courts may order that the OBC be disclosed to adult adoptees, without notice to the birth/first parents.

<br><b>7. Birth/first parents have had many years to prepare for the possibility that their adult offspring may seek contact.</b><br>
You cannot live in modern society without reading a news article or seeing a television show portraying an adoptee search and reunion story. The media love these stories, probably because they touch such a basic human need for people to be connected to family and blood. As such, they are very popular.
Birth/first parents are people who live in society, too. Many birth/first parents actually choose to search. And since access is only available to adult adoptees, birth/first parents have had at least two decades to prepare for, think about, and plan for the possibility of contact from their offspring. They are not frightened teenagers any more. They are mature adults.

<br><b>7.  Many birth/first mothers were banished and shamed into relinquishing their children.</b><br>
The small percentage of birth/first mothers who prefer no contact almost always do so as a result of the trauma they endured at the hands of society and their families.
The sad truth is that many birth/first mothers weren’t “promised privacy” but were shamed, banished and forced to relinquish their babies. It is a disgraceful part of United States history that during the “Baby Scoop Era” (1945-1970s) many unmarried women were subject to forceful and degrading tactics to convince them to surrender their children. Ann Fessler in her moving book The Girls Who Went Away, the tactics of the Baby Scoop Era.

And the fact that birth/first mothers (and pretty much all people, for that matter) want privacy from the public regarding their personal affairs, does not mean they want anonymity from their adult offspring. There are plenty of things you don’t want on the front page of the Hartford Courant that it’s okay for your family to know.
We as a state and a society aren’t breaking promises, but awakening to the collective damage inflicted upon a generation of unmarried, pregnant women. In March, 2013 Australian Prime Minister Australia Julia Gillard issued a national apology to birth/first mothers for practices of forced adoption in that country during the Baby Scoop Era.
Today well over 90% of adoption arrangements involve at least some openness and contact between birth and adoptive families.  This speaks to the psychological and cultural awareness that an adoptee’s knowledge of biological origins promotes the well-being of all parties involved, independent of the issue of their legal right to this knowledge when they become adults.
Not one surrender document has ever been produced that indicates that birth/first parents were “promised privacy” in Connecticut.

<br><h1>About Adoptive Parents…</h1><br>

1. Adoptees and adoptive parents are natural allies, not natural enemies.
Again please remember that adult adoptees are not, as a group, idiots or insensitive louts. Adoptees instead tend to be quite sensitive to the possible concerns of their adoptive parents. Remember adoptive parents are the adoptee’s family, and people tend to care about their families.
An adult adoptee seeking his OBC is looking for their own history and identity, not rejecting their adoptive parents.

2. Most adoptive parents support adult adoptee access.
Most parents want what is best for their children. This is true even after the child grows into an adult. And adoptive parents are parents.  This recent survey in New York State of over 1200 adoptive parents found that the majority supported adult adoptee access to their original birth certificates (including retroactive access).

Want to learn even more? Go to our research page.


        ]]>
    </string>


    <string name="position_statement" formatted="false">
        <![CDATA[


          <h1> Our Position Statement
on
Access to Original Birth Certificates</h1>

<br>Access Connecticut supports a proposal for legislation that would build on a law passed in 2014 and restore the right of every adopted adult citizen in Connecticut to obtain a copy of her original, true birth certificate.

<br>The proposed legislation would:
<br>•	Require the Department of Public Health to issue an uncertified copy of an original birth certificate to an adopted person who is 18 years of age or older or the adopted person’s adult child or grandchild; and
<br>•	clarify that a person born outside of Connecticut but adopted in this state would have the right to information on his or her original birth certificate.

<br>Access Connecticut supports proposed legislation concerning access to original birth certificates, and the Connecticut General Assembly should approve the bill in the 2017 legislative session for the following reasons:

<br><b>•	Recent experience and authority.</b> The legislation would restore a right that existed until 1975 for all adult adoptees in Connecticut to access their original birth certificates. It would expand on Public Act 14-133, which requires the Department of Public Health to provide adopted individuals age 18 or older whose adoptions were finalized on or after October 1, 1983, or their adult children or grandchildren, uncertified copies of the adoptee\'s original birth certificate on request. Since 1975, access to original birth certificates could only be obtained through a probate court order. Under the new state law, persons adopted before Oct. 1, 1983, their adult children or grandchildren, or certain relatives of a deceased adoptee can also obtain the original certificate, through a court order. Other states have enacted similar legislation recently and have not experienced any of the feared consequences.<br>

<br><b>•	Widespread support.</b> Numerous studies and experience in Connecticut and nationally show that 90-95% of birth mothers want and consent to contact with their adult offspring. The vast majority of adoptive parents (80%-90%) support access for adult adoptees. More than four out of five Connecticut residents (85%) support a law allowing adult adoptees to obtain copies of their original birth certificates naming their birth parents, according to a study conducted by the University of Connecticut Center for Survey Research and Analysis.

<br><b>•	Myth and misinformation.</b> Birth parent anonymity is a complete illusion and fiction. Since 1987, pursuant to state law, identifying information regarding a birth parent is disclosed to an adult adoptee who has requested it upon the death of the birth parent. Increasingly, adoptees are locating their biological relatives through the Internet, social media and DNA testing. Since 1983, every parent voluntarily relinquishing her parental rights in Connecticut has signed an Affidavit of Consent acknowledging her offspring may have the right to identifying information once they become adults. Birth mothers were not offered a choice nor guaranteed lifelong anonymity. Courts that have addressed challenges to open access laws have held that birth parents do not have a right to anonymity from their offspring.

<br><b>•	Health history is vital to adoptees.</b> Obtaining medical health history information of birth parents is vital to the life and health of adult adoptees and their descendants. The legislation would allow such information to be provided voluntarily by birth parents and be furnished by the Department of Children and Families.

<br><b>•	Positive fiscal impact.</b> Administering and furnishing birth certificates and contact preference and health history forms, according to the Office of Fiscal Analysis, would not impose a significant cost or administrative burden on the state or agencies affected. Indeed, the new law is “anticipated to result in a net state revenue gain” (emphasis added). Additionally, based on data from other states, it is estimated that fees for original birth certificates would generate a significant positive revenue impact in the first few years after enactment that would more than offset any cost associated with administering the records.

<br><b>•	Equal protection under the law.</b> Adopted persons should be treated and protected like any other ordinary person who can obtain his original birth certificate. The state should not make distinctions between otherwise similarly situated individuals.

<br><b>•	Protects birth parent privacy.</b> The new law requires the Department of Children and Families to provide birth parents with a contact preference form, allowing them to express, in regard to the adopted person, their preference for contact, contact through an intermediary, or no contact. This private method of communication reduces the likelihood of public exposure that increasingly occurs as adoptees turn to social media to search for their birth parents. Some social media searches by adult adoptees on Facebook have generated more than one million views.

<br><br>Please contact Karen Caffrey, President of Access Connecticut Now, Inc., at (860) 306-0900, with any questions or for additional information about the legislation.


        ]]>
    </string>

</resources>
