<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Access Connecticut</string>

    <string name="position_statement" formatted="false">
        <![CDATA[


          <h1> Our Position Statement </h1>
on
Access to Original Birth Certificates

Access Connecticut supports a proposal for legislation that would build on a law passed in 2014 and restore the right of every adopted adult citizen in Connecticut to obtain a copy of her original, true birth certificate.

The proposed legislation would:
•	Require the Department of Public Health to issue an uncertified copy of an original birth certificate to an adopted person who is 18 years of age or older or the adopted person’s adult child or grandchild; and
•	clarify that a person born outside of Connecticut but adopted in this state would have the right to information on his or her original birth certificate.

Access Connecticut supports proposed legislation concerning access to original birth certificates, and the Connecticut General Assembly should approve the bill in the 2017 legislative session for the following reasons:

•	Recent experience and authority. The legislation would restore a right that existed until 1975 for all adult adoptees in Connecticut to access their original birth certificates. It would expand on Public Act 14-133, which requires the Department of Public Health to provide adopted individuals age 18 or older whose adoptions were finalized on or after October 1, 1983, or their adult children or grandchildren, uncertified copies of the adoptee\'s original birth certificate on request. Since 1975, access to original birth certificates could only be obtained through a probate court order. Under the new state law, persons adopted before Oct. 1, 1983, their adult children or grandchildren, or certain relatives of a deceased adoptee can also obtain the original certificate, through a court order. Other states have enacted similar legislation recently and have not experienced any of the feared consequences.<br>

•	Widespread support. Numerous studies and experience in Connecticut and nationally show that 90-95% of birth mothers want and consent to contact with their adult offspring. The vast majority of adoptive parents (80%-90%) support access for adult adoptees. More than four out of five Connecticut residents (85%) support a law allowing adult adoptees to obtain copies of their original birth certificates naming their birth parents, according to a study conducted by the University of Connecticut Center for Survey Research and Analysis.

•	Myth and misinformation. Birth parent anonymity is a complete illusion and fiction. Since 1987, pursuant to state law, identifying information regarding a birth parent is disclosed to an adult adoptee who has requested it upon the death of the birth parent. Increasingly, adoptees are locating their biological relatives through the Internet, social media and DNA testing. Since 1983, every parent voluntarily relinquishing her parental rights in Connecticut has signed an Affidavit of Consent acknowledging her offspring may have the right to identifying information once they become adults. Birth mothers were not offered a choice nor guaranteed lifelong anonymity. Courts that have addressed challenges to open access laws have held that birth parents do not have a right to anonymity from their offspring.

•	Health history is vital to adoptees. Obtaining medical health history information of birth parents is vital to the life and health of adult adoptees and their descendants. The legislation would allow such information to be provided voluntarily by birth parents and be furnished by the Department of Children and Families.

•	Positive fiscal impact. Administering and furnishing birth certificates and contact preference and health history forms, according to the Office of Fiscal Analysis, would not impose a significant cost or administrative burden on the state or agencies affected. Indeed, the new law is “anticipated to result in a net state revenue gain” (emphasis added). Additionally, based on data from other states, it is estimated that fees for original birth certificates would generate a significant positive revenue impact in the first few years after enactment that would more than offset any cost associated with administering the records.

•	Equal protection under the law. Adopted persons should be treated and protected like any other ordinary person who can obtain his original birth certificate. The state should not make distinctions between otherwise similarly situated individuals.

•	Protects birth parent privacy. The new law requires the Department of Children and Families to provide birth parents with a contact preference form, allowing them to express, in regard to the adopted person, their preference for contact, contact through an intermediary, or no contact. This private method of communication reduces the likelihood of public exposure that increasingly occurs as adoptees turn to social media to search for their birth parents. Some social media searches by adult adoptees on Facebook have generated more than one million views.

Please contact Karen Caffrey, President of Access Connecticut Now, Inc., at (860) 306-0900, with any questions or for additional information about the legislation.


        ]]>
    </string>

</resources>
